One face.
One fleet.
One war...
One man...
Just an idea...
One trick...
The ruse that will bring down the walls of Troy.
And amid a deafening roar.
it will burn her to ashes!
What do you mean?
It's a gift.
For Athena.
My people. pay homage
to the gods through their sacrifices.
Pull him out of the water!
Take him to the Temple of Athena.
The war is over.
Stop it!
Not this song.
I want to remind them
whose wine they're drinking.
I don't want a song about Odysseus.
I want Odysseus himself.
So why do you
welcome them into his home every evening?
In this world. men do whatever they want.
And women are doing what they can.
I'm a man now. Mom.
Then kick them out.
They're breaking Dia's law.
All it takes is an excuse. and they'll attack you.
I've already lost my husband.
I don't want to lose my son. too.
My father will come back.
So where is he?
Eight years have passed since the fall of Troy.
And it's been almost twenty years since he left.
Where is it?
We must welcome him just
as we welcome each one of you.
Are you calling us beggars?
I'm saying you've been guests here for three years now.
Soon we'll be relying
on your hospitality.
Because your mother can't make up her mind.
She's already married.
Odysseus is dead.
And what do you know about my father?
I know he left you
nothing but flocks and old wine.
You managed to miss the best part
during the first two years.
And I know he never came home.
Not yet.
You're still clinging to your father.
whom you never even knew.
What a pathetic kid.
Since none of us can know.
Whoever his father is.
don't claim to know mine.
But I knew him.
When we were little. we used to watch him on his hunting trips.
I volunteered
to join his expedition to Troy.
He asked me to stay here
and keep an eye on you.
At me or at my mother?
You can't blame me for my happiness.
My father will come back.
And then his hospitality
won't be like hers.
So would he be breaking Dia's law?
God's law commands us
to treat strangers in such a way that
just as we would like them to treat us.
They might be gods in disguise.
I think we can agree. Antinous.
that you are definitely not a god.
And this one definitely doesn't smell like a god.
If he were. his disguise
wouldn't be very convincing.
Be careful—
he might strike you down with lightning right on the spot.
That thunder was just a coincidence.
I don't know.
You have wise eyes…
eyes like Athena's.
Look. do you see all those traitors?
From Sparta.
Has Menelaus returned from the war?
Years ago.
But Odysseus never returned.
We don't even know if he's still alive.
Did you hear anything?
Songs about his victory in the war.
We've all heard those.
Anything else?
No.
But Sparta is full of old warriors
from Troy.
Someone must know something.
Are you Odysseus's son?
Go to Sparta.
Go see Menelaus.
He'll welcome you.
The queen wants to speak with the stranger.
He lives only for the news.
Just don't try to
give her false hope.
He has his own way of finding out
whether anyone has actually seen *The Odyssey*.
Do you see that man?
He doesn't see very well anymore.
but that doesn't stop him
to kill the pilgrims for the lies
they spread about my father.
Slow down. slow down—it's too fast.
And how did you know that?
I don't need eyes
to hear your hurried heartbeat.
Mentor. put some pressure on him.
Too fast.
He's just as friendly as you are.
He only listened to your father.
Where did he bring him from?
He found him here.
I'll take it.
For your son?
Like a hunting dog.
Damn it. it looks like he was right.
Stop!
How deep do you want the cut to be?
Why do you always push people's buttons like that?
It's a matter of honor.
To warn your prey?
So that she may fight with honor.
You weren't fighting; you were hunting.
Hunting cannot be compared
to a battle where cunning is the deciding factor.
Cunning. cunning…
but that cunning will come back to haunt you one day.
Try again.
But this time.
don't be too hasty or too precise.
You don't win with perfect defense.
Provoke an attack.
How?
Hesitate.
Leave his stomach exposed.
That way. his attack
will become your opportunity.
Is this what you taught my father?
No. no. he's the one who taught me.
He said. “You won’t always be the strongest.”
"Not even the fastest.
so be the smartest."
What do you think he would do?
What if he came back and found
all those suitors in the house?
I can't even imagine
what he would do to them.
There are a lot of them.
Get rid of two.
and the rest will fall apart.
They're just a bunch of blowhards and cowards.
Most of them were old enough to go
to Troy. but when they saw Agamemnon’s
sails. their fathers hid them.
Their fathers hid them.
And did you know
that Agamemnon's war
It will take years
and claim many lives.
Therefore. he assembled his army by drawing lots.
Name?
Sinon.
Pull.
No.
Name?
Antinous.
Pull.
Yes.
By drawing lots?
Antinous told me
that he had volunteered.
One boy wants to take Sinon's place.
I won't let that happen.
He has to stay here
and take care of his family.
You. too. can take care of your son.
Of course.
He's with me.
Is this what Odysseus wanted. Antinous—
for you to keep an eye on me?
No. no. no.
But Odysseus
understood his fathers' shame.
He felt sorry for those fathers.
You and your mother were
more important to him than the promise of fame.
So he knew it would take years.
Did he tell my mother that?
That's a question for her.
You might be wondering
if he'll ever come back at all.
Argos believes that.
I've never seen a dog
live to be twenty years old.
And so he outlived his master.
I didn't mean to interrupt you.
I'm in no hurry.
The elders decided
that once I finish
Weaving a burial shroud for your grandfather—
it will be time to set out again.
Why?
Ithaca had been without a king for too long.
They want safety.
How long ago?
Before the Sea Nations.
These are just stories told by pilgrims.
Everything we know about the world
comes from the stories of travelers.
That's how we learned that Troy had fallen.
Now everyone is telling stories
about the raids by the Sea Peoples.
Who are the Sea Peoples?
No one knows. but the elders wanted
us to be prepared.
Ready?
We are part of the greatest civilization
the world has ever known.
Look at this huge palace.
Stones as old as time itself. left at the mercy
of greedy. unwelcome guests.
This building is worthless
without people's respect
for her legacy.
The Law of Dia.
Treat others the way
you want them to treat you.
And when they abuse it. they destroy everything.
How did you even come up with the idea
to marry one of them?
Because your father asked me to
a long time ago.
Agamemnon is our king.
The Trojans took his brother's wife.
Or perhaps she left with him on her own.
In any case. the walls of Troy
are said to be impregnable.
We'll stay on the outskirts of the big city
and try to lure them out into battle.
As the years go by.
Telemachus will grow up
and you'll get used
to life without me.
Menelaus will give up Helen.
It's just an excuse for Agamemnon
to gain
Troy's control
over the trade routes.
He won't let it go.
Never.
What if you refuse?
She's going to marry our son.
He won't do that.
He sacrificed his daughter
to ensure a favorable wind.
Why would the gods want
his daughter's life?
The Value of Sacrifice
lies in the price
paid by the one who brings it.
That's terrible.
And he did it.
I won't be back anytime soon.
if I ever come back at all.
What if we ran away?
On your fastest ship.
with your best men.
and would we disappear over the horizon?
Holding hands on deck.
rowing into the sunset…
There is a world beyond these walls as well.
But Agamemnon's Revenge
would weigh down on all of Ithaca.
Promise me.
If I don't return. and when Telemachus comes of age.
promise me.
that you're going to marry someone else.
There have been enough victims already.
Love is not a sacrifice.
It is.
And I don't want you to bring it.
It's not up to you to decide.
Promise me.
No.
Promise me you'll come back.
What if I can't?
I won't live on just memories of you.
Take my brooch.
Always wear it.
Athena will bring you home.
I don't think it suits me.
I will ask every pilgrim who claims
to have seen you.
what you were wearing.
and I'll know if he's lying.
If the Sea Peoples really existed.
Then Ithaca is without a king…
and faces an army of suitors.
I can keep this hall in order.
Come on.
Draw the bow.
That's not fair.
You said that
only your father could make him get worked up.
He was happy to let others try it. too.
And he lined up all the axes.
And no one else has ever managed to do it.
Mom. they're wearing you out.
forcing you to choose
before I can
lay claim to the throne.
The stranger said
that Menelaus had returned years ago.
They all came back.
The survivors.
Maybe he died.
And if he's dead.
this palace is mine.
We need to find out the truth.
I have to go see Menelaus
to find out the truth.
It's not because these suitors
pose a threat to you.
Do you think I don't know that?
Every night they pressure me
to give them the excuse they're waiting for.
Whether at sea or on the road.
They won't need any excuse.
You won't come back.
You don't want me to lay claim to the throne.
You want me to stay in the background.
just so you can remain the queen of Ithaca.
I'm tired of being the queen of Ithaca
without my king.
Without their king?
Or just without a king?
And do you think you're ready
to take your father's place?
You're still a kid.
Lower your voice. Melanthius.
Don't step on my bruises.
You're a shepherd. not a rider.
And you're just a swineherd.
Who do you think you are. talking to me like that?
I am a servant to whom my master
has entrusted his flocks.
Your master has been gone for years. you silly old man.
And your presence here is just as
unwelcome as this dog's.
Argos!
Sir. he didn't do anything.
So that stench is coming from you?
Leave that old dog alone.
Who?
Both of them.
What did you say. slave?
I got carried away.
Argos is my father's hunting dog.
His dog?
Take a look at him.
Take him away; we're trying to eat.
No. can't you see that he's suffering?
Okay.
I'll spare him the suffering.
Leave him alone!
Did you see that?
Did you all see that?
He attacked me!
And he had every right to do so!
Please!
Please. don't hurt my son.
Calm down. calm down.
Everyone. please calm down.
The boy got carried away.
Have a little compassion.
And have another glass of wine.
I'll take care of it.
It's my father's hunting dog.
And he survived to wait for Odysseus.
Okay. I'll put it
on the compost pile by the entrance.
so that he could welcome his master a little earlier.
That dog is staying outside!
Next time. think carefully
about whether you're willing to risk your life for an animal.
You're hurt.
Get the supplies ready. take them to the ships.
and don't tell anyone.
Take only those you trust.
You're going to break your mother's heart.
If I stay. they'll force me to fight.
And no one will take my side.
I have to find out what happened to my father.
The people of Ithaca will support me
if they find out that Odysseus is dead.
But the suitors will never allow it.
You won't come back alive.
Tell the Mentor to meet me
by the boats before dawn.
And what should I tell your mother?
May he hold out as long as he can.
The ship is ready.
and the tide is favorable.
You never told me
that you have wise eyes?
How is Athena doing?
Once or twice.
You haven't asked me yet where we're going.
Where are we going?
Find my father.
It's alive.
I can feel it in the wind and in the waves.
He's out there somewhere.
lost. hurt.
I don't know where.
but he's still alive.
Those dreams again?
Men who are drowning… inside.
A dark place.
The light from the fire reflects off the stone… I don't know.
Don't you want to remember?
Why don't the gods speak a language
we can understand?
And who doesn't understand thunder. fire.
a child's smile. a bountiful harvest?
You're hiding from us.
Look. who's moving that cloud?
Who is gathering those birds?
Who moves the water?
Who were you talking to?
Athena visited me again.
It tells me to remember…
and to leave.
And why would you leave?
We have everything we need right here.
How long have I been here. Kalypso?
I have a home somewhere.
And someone is waiting for me.
And how do you know that?
I don't know.
I just feel it.
Everything we have here
could last forever.
Immortality is for the gods alone.
Are you a goddess?
You want to remember. but what if
those memories destroy you?
Then my happiness wasn't real.
That's enough. no more.
But I love her.
Stop eating that lotus already.
Tell me… what do you remember?
After Troy.
Troy.
We won the war.
And then?
Ten years on that cursed coast.
We're going home.
Remember those
we left behind.
Do we have enough supplies?
We took what we needed from Troy.
One or two stops won't hurt us.
Go for it!
Get to work!
Paddles down.
Take a break!
Oars down!
Hoist the sails.
Keep an eye on the southerly winds.
Yes. sir.
Agamemnon is sailing west
along a well-known supply route.
And she has more men to feed.
We'll find places to settle down.
Are you sure?
It's a risk.
I followed Agamemnon for quite a while.
With a little luck and favorable winds.
we'll see
another world. and we'll return
before Agamemnon.
Warning!
Keep the constellation Ursa Major on your right.
Odysseus. land!
Can you see that?
You lucky bastard.
We only have our last few supplies left.
Assemble the landing party.
and bring food and water.
Everything we need for three weeks.
What if they refuse?
How much do you want to go home?
Get your weapons ready.
Please.
We'll take it.
We borrow.
And we're leaving.
Ask him why they left the village
instead of welcoming us.
He says they thought
we were the Sea Peoples.
No. we're Greeks from Ithaca.
You may have heard
about our victory at Troy.
With the southerly winds. we're sailing west.
He says that if you go that way.
you won't like what you find.
After years of war
No one will stop my men
on their way home.
Neither do I.
Nothing happened?
We're chasing the setting sun.
You found him.
You lucky bastard.
No. no. no. no. no.
The sheep are not alone.
Let's go after them.
Someone must live here.
Yes. they make cheese.
It's delicious.
And there's plenty of it.
We have to leave.
We didn't bring anything to trade.
It is Dia's law.
I don't know if the owner is familiar with
the Law of Dia. or even knows who Dia is.
Everyone knows the Law of Dia.
Build a fire.
We'll wait until the owner comes back.
Away from the fire.
No. no!
Take a break!
I think he's asleep.
Wait a minute.
Don't look.
We can't move that rock.
He'll lock us up here.
Tell everyone that this morning.
As soon as he herds the flock outside.
we'll head for the entrance.
Stay close to the wall.
No. no. no. no. no. no!
Run!
Is there anything we can use to block the entrance to the cave?
Leave only the opening.
Maybe.
But how?
It's closed.
He'll notice that.
Grab the thin end
and put it in the fire.
How many ropes do we have left?
How big is that herd?
About twenty. maybe.
There are too many of us.
When he comes back.
two of us have to run outside.
To let oneself be killed.
Run low through the herd toward the exit
and then split up.
That way. he'll catch only one.
That's right.
Four of us have to give it a try.
Two and two.
Why risk more men?
Last night. there were two fewer of us.
We'll let the others know
before they fall asleep.
Run! Run! Run!
And what about his body?
What happened?
Are we just going to let him rot here?
Leave him as food
for that monster?
We honor our dead. Odysseus.
He died to help us escape.
And we'll honor him by running away.
Father Poseidon. they've blinded me.
Avenge me. Father. Avenge my pain.
Poseidon. avenge my pain.
He says.
Why didn't he say anything before?
Do you talk to ants?
Should we try to work something out?
I think we've already gotten past that phase.
What are you doing?
No!
Let's go. Run. run!
Let's go!
Hop on!
Get moving!
Come on. come on!
Let's go!
Why did you shoot that arrow?
Because of that monster. we lost
some brave men.
Yes. and that monster was the son of Poseidon.
What?
When we gouged out his eye. we heard him
call out his father's name.
That thing was a monster.
I heard that. too.
So has the sea become our enemy?
Even the wind.
How will we get home
if Poseidon hates us?
We cannot live under the yoke
of promises and sacrifices.
Do you know how many times you've heard me
to weep and beg Athena—
ever since we left Troy?
Couldn't you have shown a little compassion?
Take this.
Wear this to remember those
whom we could not bury.
The gods help those
who help themselves.
From that moment on. every rough stretch of water
or headwind
He tried to convince the crew
that we were haunted by a curse.
But where's my crew?
When will you let me see my men?
If I could talk to them.
they would help me remember.
Did I have a wife? Children?
Maybe a son?
How long have I been here?
Too long.
If I had a son.
how old would he be now?
I don't know how to talk to the king.
You'll be fine.
Just be quiet.
But if we're asked…
Let's say we're merchants from Crete.
and then we'll see
how we'll approach it.
Welcome.
Thank you.
It looks like you're having fun.
This way.
Where are you taking us?
The king insists
that he meet with the foreigners in person.
Have a seat.
Not you.
You.
Enjoy our hospitality.
just as men should.
But maybe you could tell us who you are.
You came on the right day.
We're celebrating my daughter's wedding.
And tomorrow she's leaving to start a new life.
You don't look like a beggar.
Let's assume you know who I am.
Menelaus. son of Atreus.
and brother of Agamemnon.
And Helena's husband.
He must have heard about Helena.
That face…
She sent out a thousand ships.
And maybe there are only five hundred of them left now.
All those who fell on the plains of Troy
for that face.
Because of your brother's ambition.
That sounds familiar to me.
Aias.
Patroclus…
Achilles…
I don't miss them as much as I miss a single warrior.
He was the smartest of us all.
We languished on that coast for ten years.
No progress on either side.
We used to argue among ourselves.
until one day…
He found a solution.
Odysseus.
Have you heard the story about the horse?
Or do you want to hear it
from someone who was inside?
We stayed there for days on end.
They were crammed into the horse-drawn carriage
before it was pulled into town.
Odysseus knew
that no one must know about us.
not even that soldier.
whom we left behind there.
During the first two high tides.
we almost drowned.
We remained silent.
We were suffocating in our own feces.
A sacrifice to Athena.
Because the gods honor those
who make offerings to them.
We have to burn it.
Burn him! Burn him!
It is an offering to Athena.
Goal!
And he knew when. that night.
to slip out from behind the walls of Troy.
Let's go! Let's go!
To the gates!
Run!
Hurry!
Come on. hurry up!
I think you know the rest of the story.
Did my story move you?
Does my story move you?
Then you should hear the poets.
I've seen a lot.
But I wasn't with you.
Your father… Odysseus.
Do you still remember him?
When was the last time you saw him?
In Troy.
The gods granted us a well-deserved victory.
Is that fair?
The gods granted us a just victory.
but they did not bless our journey home.
My return took years;
his never happened.
Others returned
and wished it hadn't happened.
Tell him.
Tell him about your brother.
No.
Tell him what fate the gods
have in store for him after his glorious victory.
No.
Tell him how they welcomed him as a hero.
No!
Tell him how Agamemnon
returned home years before us.
Tell him how his wife.
my twin. Clytemnestra. welcomed him.
No… no… no.
Tell him how… No!
He doesn't want to hear about my brother!
And what about his father?
I don't know anything about Odysseus from Troy.
Nothing?
Not even from any of your men?
Not even from Agamemnon’s men.
traitors. or travelers?
Did you come here because of the rumors?
Is that why you came?
Because of the gossip?
Then you've come to the right place.
Do any of you have
a story about Odysseus?
Some say he's rich.
others say he's poor.
Some say he died.
others say he was captured.
What do you think?
Captured?
What prison could hold a man like that?
Tell me what you remember.
And the rest will follow.
And the men began to believe
that I had angered Poseidon.
Ready!
Row!
Storms came one after another
and led us off course.
until we lost all sense of direction.
Hey!
We came in peace.
We just need a little food.
We need food.
Do you understand?
He's just a child.
If this is a child.
then what are his or her parents like?
Calm down… calm down. everything's fine.
No. no. no. no.
Calm… calm.
Back to the ship!
Come on. back! Back! Let's go!
Damn!
Run! Faster!
To the ship! To the ship!
Let's go!
Let's go! Let's go!
Row!
Wait!
Run!
Run. for heaven's sake!
Turn left and follow the coastline.
What if they have ships?
We have to get as far as possible.
We don't have enough supplies to sail
across the sea with no land in sight.
We're lost.
We need to find some food
and figure out where we are.
Turn left.
There!
Smoke… over there!
Go around it; we'll anchor off the coast.
Warning!
Assemble the landing party.
Tomorrow.
Have someone stay with the boats.
We agreed that you should stay.
Did you agree?
Everyone.
As long as we live.
Is this a rebellion?
That's up to you.
Give me your bow.
I'll make sure
we have something to eat tonight.
Whatever you find there.
No. no. no. okay!
All right!
You're safe!
Everything's fine!
No one will hurt you!
No one will hurt you.
My name is Eurylochus.
what's your name?
Circe.
Circe. we really need some food.
I have some food.
A lot of food.
May I?
Put down your weapons.
Even the shields.
Leave them outside the door.
Did you like my meat?
Why do you have all of this?
No one knows when the strangers will arrive.
Men.
Their appetite is insatiable.
They can never get enough of them.
Eurylochus.
They haven't come back yet.
Not a single one.
No.
Give me your knife.
Stay by the boat.
Why don't you come in?
Are you coming from the sea?
Are you alone?
It seems my pigs have taken a liking to you.
Are you hungry?
Leave your weapon by the door.
And enjoy Dio's hospitality.
Catch that bastard.
You can serve it for dinner.
Whoever you are.
you're definitely not a farmer.
You're welcome.
That goulash looks delicious.
There's just enough for us.
Who said we're alone?
Who else is here?
That's a good question.
You say you're alone.
but no one comes here alone.
That's right.
Because there is no road leading here.
only the sea.
So where are your companions. then?
I'm looking for them.
Has anyone been through here?
But you prepared all this food.
Are you hearing my confession?
You. me?
A starving pilgrim
who won't touch the food in front of him.
And he claims to be a sailor.
but he wears the armor of a great warrior.
And he breaks Dia's law by bringing
a knife into his hostess's house.
You have keen eyes.
The gods filed them down for me.
And do they give you foresight?
More like the truth.
Sometimes.
And they'll tell you.
"Where can I find my men?"
Your men?
Yes.
You'll tell me.
So. are you going to tell me?
Maybe.
If you give me your knife.
Why would I help a liar
who refuses my hospitality?
Your men were here just a moment ago.
No… they aren't.
Did they leave?
Yes.
And did they leave their rings here?
I wouldn't do that.
Don't do that.
I don't know who this stranger is to you.
But if you don't drop the knife.
I'll keep choking her until I find out.
Don't touch her.
Is she a relative of yours?
Your mother?
Your sister?
Did you do the same thing to her
as you did to my husband?
Did you turn them into pigs?
I didn't turn
your men into anything.
Take a look at them.
That's what they really look like…
Their filthy. animalistic instincts…
the very ones you glorify in war.
Because of you. they raped and plundered the world.
And don't you think that's what they're all about?
Do you think they did all that
just because you told them to?
A true leader convinces himself that the brutality
of his men is merely discipline.
But you don't seem naive.
And yet You sent them to me
when I was alone.
A handful of dirty soldiers.
hungry. with boiling blood in their veins.
Did he think they would respect
me and my home?
Take a look at them and discover
the truth about your men.
Did someone hurt you?
They would hurt someone.
They just want to go home.
Let them come back.
Come back. come back. come back.
Return to your true form.
Return.
return to your true form.
Come back. come back. come back.
Return to your true form.
Odysseus. let's go to the ship.
Take as much food as you can carry.
and leave the meat alone.
You won't let her live—she's a witch.
Who gave her this power?
The Gods.
Fill the jugs and containers from the stream.
At dawn. get ready to set sail.
Why are you letting her do that?
We're better off this way.
I apologize if we offended you.
We won't leave without your help.
We need a route
to the trade routes.
You've wandered around long enough.
What do you mean?
No one but the seer Teiresias
will show you the way.
Teiresias?
In Hád.
No one can go to Hades
and come back.
But you'll come back.
Head north to the Land of Twilight.
Then walk along the land until the river of fire
meets the river of ice.
Dig a trench there.
And fill it with the blood of the sacrifice.
And gather the souls of the dead.
Then you'll find out how to get home.
You.
Your men aren't.
Do you curse them?
That's not a curse.
That's true.
Your men don't want
you to provoke the gods.
Because the gods say
that only you will return home.
Then I'll provoke the gods.
Sinon.
I am Odysseus.
Let him have a drink. Odysseus.
And then you'll hear his testimony.
Odysseus.
Yes.
You lied to everyone.
Or were you supposed to lie to me?
I had to convince you.
Why did you sign up voluntarily?
Do you remember how I got here?
I asked if I could
take Antino's place.
He was selected by lottery.
And he offered your family money
if you took his place.
Unless the Trojans let me live.
And if I don't come home.
Give this to my father.
And tell him what I did.
Odysseus.
And don't hesitate to add a few details.
You didn't trust me enough
to tell me the truth.
You knew I would die for you.
I had to convince you.
I died because of your lie
on that shore.
I know.
I was there with you.
And I heard you tell that lie
as you were dying. and we won the war.
I was just a few steps away from you.
I could smell your blood.
And what comfort is that supposed to give me?
I didn't know you were in on it
until the dead told me.
Which dead people?
There are a lot of your kind wandering around here.
The dead are gathering
to mourn the living
and welcomed the newcomers.
And my father was the first to come to me.
To comfort you?
Souls do not bring comfort.
They are looking for those who have been wronged by the living.
My father died poor and alone.
begging for crumbs
from people like Antinous.
Did Antinous cheat on you?
And he's definitely cheating on you. too.
How?
Who is taking care of your wife
and son in Ithaca?
I'm not worried about my wife.
Talk to Agamemnon about returning home.
Is Agamemnon here?
You buried me with honor in Troy;
thank you.
But think also of those
whom you have not buried.
That's not always possible.
When you get home.
Take a boat and sail westward. into the unknown.
until you reach land.
And there. offer sacrifices
and honor your men.
Do you still have that lottery ticket?
Of course.
When you get home.
let Antinoo taste humiliation.
I'll do it.
My lord.
Odysseus.
How did you get here?
We won the war.
and you were on your way home.
Odysseus. the most brilliant
of all my commanders.
They wouldn't have caught you in a trap the way they caught me.
Did the waves wash you ashore just like us?
No. my misfortune was
that I returned home.
So that my beautiful wife can welcome me.
She washed me.
And she put on some perfume.
And I calmed down.
Then she taught me the hardest lesson.
I planted poison in her heart
years ago.
No! No!
And a large part of her heart had rotted away…
For years. she conspired with her lover
to kill me.
Odysseus… Yes.
Did my son Orestes… avenge me?
My goodness. how am I supposed to know that?
I'm still trying to get home.
Don't make the same mistake I did.
Don't walk in through the front door. and don't expect
wreaths and praise.
Enter secretly.
Make time for it.
Gather your strength.
What do you see?
I know what I have to do.
You know only part of what you need to do.
My prophecy is not meant for their ears.
Go back to the ship.
Sail southwest.
around Siren Island.
They lure men onto the cliffs.
Everyone will die.
I won't let that happen.
I'll plug their ears with wax.
Beyond the Sirens. you must choose between the whirlpool
of Charybdis and the monster Scylla.
The whirlpool in the sea will swallow you all up.
The monster hiding in the rocks
will kill only six.
But your stubborn refusal to sacrifice even
your soul will kill them all.
I'll do whatever it takes.
And finally. when you're threatened by hunger and rebellion.
They will ask you to land on the island
where the Sun God grazes his cattle.
If they kill Apollo's cattle...
Zeus will destroy them as punishment.
What do you see?
I'll stop them.
Why do you value the lives of these men
more than the ones you've already lost?
I can still save them from the gods.
But not in front of them.
What is it?
These are the members of your crew
who were not buried.
They're calling on you to share in their shame.
Let's go. hurry up!
Untie the ropes!
We have to set sail!
Is that our goal?
Is this our fate?
We left Hades and lost
many species.
I have to save those who are left.
What happened to them?
Did they leave me here?
Will they come back?
Did you do something to them?
Go ahead.
You told me
not to eat the lotus flower.
Just for tonight. so you can get some sleep.
And tomorrow. when you're ready.
you'll remember.
You'll think of your crew
and your family.
Family?
A woman?
Do I have a wife?
What are you doing?
It's okay. Melanthó.
Foreigners are not allowed here.
Whether there's a curtain or not. after three years
of feasting. we're no longer strangers here.
Do you want to marry me.
or ruin my reputation?
Melanthó knows how to keep a secret.
Actually. I came
because of your reputation.
Really?
Everyone can see how hard you're trying.
Slowly but surely.
But every night you unravel
what you wove during the day.
Leave us alone.
You can't expect her to.
that she would be faithful to the man
she had never met.
I expect her to be faithful to me.
And it will be. when you marry me.
Children have no other choice
but to remain faithful to the future.
And this house is waiting for its master.
just as Ithaca awaits its king.
The King of Ithaca will return.
No. he won't.
Did you know that when I was a kid. I tried
to go with him to Troy?
He never told me that.
Laertes refused to let me go.
He knew that Ithaca needed
a future without him.
And he saw that I am part of
that future.
I won't tell the other suitors
about your deception.
Continue weaving.
It's time to let it go.
Why would you marry someone
who wants someone else?
Your loyalty to the House of Laertus
is your most valuable quality.
I love you.
I want you to choose me
and put an end to this.
Don't say you're not tired.
The waiting… and the uncertainty.
You have fulfilled your duty
year after year.
It's time to think about yourself.
It's time to live again.
Laertes wouldn't want that.
I'll take care of all your needs.
My queen.
And what about my son?
The throne is his.
He is the heir.
Unless the two of us have a child.
Where is Telemachus?
He went inland
to visit his grandfather.
He's lying.
He set sail.
He went to find out what was going on with his father.
Where?
He went to Sparta.
To Menelaus.
Okay. shall we go there?
No.
Your voice is too loud. Melanthius.
I told you you're a coward.
He was listening to us.
No. no.
I came to pick up Argos.
I told you that the dog would stay there.
Go back to the farm.
And when we need pigs.
we'll send for you. Melanthius.
You are no longer welcome in this palace. old man.
I was following my mistress's orders.
Do you even know your name?
Get out.
Telemachus will have to return
through the temple at Pylos.
Go there with your men.
So that you can stay here
and compete for the queen?
I don't think so.
He must die on the road.
And Eurymachus has a plan.
Eurymachus.
I want everyone who falls
into the trap to be dead.
Thrown into a pit with their throats slit.
Telemachus and his men
will be ready
against the bandits who are running rampant
on the road between Ithaca and Pylos.
But what if some of them arrive
at the temple before them?
Then bring me proof
of Telemachus's death.
His nose.
And you'll recognize him just by his nose?
Even by the ears.
Who taught you?
My father's pig herder.
A pig herder?
He was the most loyal of his servants.
Odysseus left behind
his most loyal servants.
He was always the smartest of them all.
And the only one Agamemnon listened to.
I wish I had listened to him more.
May I ask
what happened to your brother?
His wife betrayed him and killed him.
And what happened to her?
His son Orestes killed them both.
Did he kill his mother?
He avenged his father.
But don't worry.
Your mother is nothing
like Clytemnestra.
Maybe not. but the suitors
convinced the elders.
that it's time for her to get married again.
Yes. it is not wise
for the throne to remain empty.
I've heard stories…
about the Sea Peoples.
Have you been attacked?
Not yet. but the attacks are coming.
Sparta is ready.
And Ithaca?
He can raise an army
and defend himself.
But someone has to take the throne.
Then you must fight there. not here. my son.
You ran away from the problem.
And he left his mother
at the mercy of her suitors.
Should I hire mercenaries and go back
to kill them all?
Kill the rich and powerful
guests in your own home?
They will drive you into exile.
And then what?
You must drive them out without
breaking the law of Dia.
I must take the throne.
And I have to find out
if Odysseus is still alive.
This has nothing to do with his father.
whom he never knew.
You must lead. my son.
no matter what fate awaits Odysseus.
You have to remember.
No. I don't want to.
I don't need to know the truth.
I'm happy here with you.
Then why are you gathering the wreckage of your
old ship to build a raft?
Think about your crew…
and think back on your journey.
I heard the song "Sirens."
Plug your ears with wax. guys.
Not me.
Tie me to the mast.
Why?
I want to hear the song "Sirén."
No.
That's a bad idea.
No one survived
who heard their song.
That's why it's a good idea.
I'll be the first to do it.
No matter how much I beg you.
don't untie me until we've sailed past.
Take care of the earwax in men's ears.
A double serving for anyone
who objects!
What was the song "Sirén" like?
Everything you've ever wanted.
And then everything you ever wished for—
things you wish you’d never wished for.
It was like a delightful itch.
one that makes you want to scratch.
You'll find it beneath the skin. and the more
you touch it. the more you want it.
And that amazing feeling becomes unbearable.
Didn't I tell you that what
you want most.
Is it something you can't have?
And what you can't have
is what you once had.
And you lost it.
It was a song about all the promises
I hadn't kept.
And they told me that. in fact.
I don't want to go home.
Currents!
Currents ahead!
Charybdis.
A wild whirlpool.
Take down the sails!
Let's go. hurry up!
Take the helm!
When we set sail.
It's already pulling us in.
To the ropes!
We have to go north! Hurry up!
Maybe we'll make it to that strait.
It's too narrow.
Head toward the vortex.
If we turn the boat sideways toward the slope.
we'll gain enough speed to
get to the other side.
Don't worry. we'll manage.
No. no!
We're heading toward the canal.
Quiet! We're heading toward the canal!
Pull in the oars!
Oars down!
Starboard oars. get ready
to stop the boat!
On my command!
Three!
Two!
One!
Go for it!
Pull on the oars!
Hang in there!
We did it!
We did it. The gods are with us.
Row!
Keep the boat on an even keel!
Keep the boat steady!
Go for it!
You knew it!
And you didn't tell us anything!
If I told you that.
you wouldn't choose this path.
And those men would be alive!
No!
We would all die!
You had no right to do that!
It was my full right!
And I take full responsibility!
The whirlpool would have destroyed the ship
and drowned all of us!
That's how we survived!
Some of us!
Yes!
What else did Teiresias tell you?
We'll drop anchor there!
We can't land there!
It's the island of the Sun God!
We need repairs!
These men are exhausted!
We've lost six of our own!
We'll drop anchor and take a break on land.
You're all going to die!
You're asking me what Teiresias told me?
He said you'll all die
if you kill
the Sun God's cattle.
which graze on that island.
You're all going to die!
It's okay.
We'll drop anchor and cook
our own provisions.
We'll pick some fruit. bring some water.
and nothing else.
Everyone. swear to it.
See?
The wind blew us right here.
We'll take a break. repair the boat.
and set sail as soon as the wind changes.
Grab that rope.
Did the crew keep their oath?
Yes. but not for long.
But the wind never changed.
The strong breeze that allowed us to anchor
made it impossible…
prevented it from sailing away.
And we ran out of supplies.
Run away!
Did you think that if you ate quietly.
the Sun God wouldn't notice?
We thought you wouldn't notice.
I'm not the problem.
I wanted you to live.
Teiresias warned you.
Circe warned you.
The gods have warned you.
You gods do not speak a language
that we understand.
And who doesn't understand pain. blood. or death?
When you see your men dying.
Do you see this as a coincidence. or as
a consequence of their actions?
I see the consequences in this…
and my own failure.
What if their death isn't
your failure. but theirs?
I'm leading them.
I brought them here.
And who brought you here?
Why do you set yourself above the gods?
Why are you taking all the blame?
Why don't you want to go home?
What are you waiting for?
Finish it.
Show them a little compassion.
My mercy has led us
to this cursed island.
I told you what would happen.
"Yes." he said.
And we decided that death by drowning
is better than death by starvation.
All right. here's your chance.
The winds have died down!
That silence was a trap meant to
draw us into Poseidon’s embrace.
under the sky of Zeus.
We're going to die!
Face the wind!
Against the wind!
Odysseus!
Get out of the way!
Surrender yourselves to the gods!
Call on Poseidon!
Just ask the gods for forgiveness!
Watch out!
The last thing I remember
was Zeus's cruel punishment.
Dorycus!
I don't know what happened to my men.
You know.
Exactly what
I had warned them about happened.
The waves washed me
ashore on your coast.
The waves brought the wreckage of your ship to me.
without a single member of your crew.
Half-dead and unconscious.
I watched you wander
through days that turned into weeks.
I knew that the lotus
would ease your awakening.
So that your pain
is in your body. not in your mind.
And it worked.
You really enjoyed it.
And you ate it willingly.
And while I was taking care of you.
Thank you.
Your love has found its way into my heart.
How long have I been here?
I kept telling myself
that I wouldn't give you any more.
And that you're strong enough
to remember.
How long. Kalypso?
You were so happy.
Was I happy?
We were very happy for years.
Years?
Seven years.
You gave me a lotus
and kept me here.
I saved your life.
I healed your body.
But I didn't dare
to heal your mind.
You were happy.
But your heart was always somewhere else.
And it was only natural
that your mind eventually followed it.
How could you?
The lotus clouds the mind and robs you of your will.
but it does not change your true nature.
For some reason. he wasn't
ready to go home.
I'm ready now.
And I always knew it would be that way.
Now?
When I found you. you were holding something.
And for weeks on end. he clutched it tightly in his palm.
You used to call out. mostly "Athena."
but sometimes you called out another name as well.
Penelope.
Help me get back home.
I'll help.
You're a man who wants to
be in control of your own destiny.
But you can't control that.
You must surrender to the storm.
surrender to Poseidon.
and accept his punishment.
Zeus won't let him kill you.
Surrender to fate. let go of control.
and live.
It's a leap of faith you've
never dared to take. Odysseus.
Odysseus.
Where am I?
Don't you recognize your home?
Zeus welcomes you. strangers.
How many of you are there?
Half a dozen.
Would you like some food?
And some snacks for the trip.
Where are you going?
We need pigs.
We're continuing on to Pyl.
Are you pilgrims?
Do we look like pilgrims?
My eyesight is poor.
Zeus commands me to feed you.
But the pigs aren't mine.
so I can't sell them.
Don't worry.
We have no intention of paying.
Please give my regards to your mother.
And tell her I'm sorry.
I'm sorry about what happened in Troy
and everything that happened in my name.
I'm sorry I haven't heard
from your father.
But you have messages.
It's not about where he is.
but about who he is.
And now. more than ever before. I hope
that one day I'll meet him.
Where are your dogs. old man?
I'm burning their bodies.
Can Zeus offer you some food. stranger?
Have you been attacked?
The dog saved the shepherds on your farm.
No. we burned his brothers first.
What happened to Ithaca?
Darkness.
Dia's Law is in ruins.
A kingdom without a king.
ever since my lord died.
Your master?
Odysseus.
The Hero of Troy.
But Odysseus is alive.
False hopes.
Enough. enough!
Enough. enough. enough!
Telemachus. Telemachus. Telemachus.
Telemachus?
He's in danger.
and I can't help him.
There must be others on Ithaca. too.
who are willing to help Odysseus's son.
The palace is under the control of the suitors.
No one is loyal to Odysseus anymore.
And the queen?
Beautiful and wise Penelope.
She is being held hostage by the worst kind of men.
and she will soon have to get married.
What can she do without her son?
Please write something.
What danger does Telemachus face?
He's on his way back from Sparta.
The suitors sent bandits to Pyl
to set a trap for him in the temple.
Give me some provisions for the trip.
You'll never catch up to the bandits.
If I get to Pyl before Telemachus.
I can warn him.
Why do you help?
Promise me you won't get mad when I tell you this
I served with Odysseus at Troy.
Really?
He was a strict commander.
But he was fair.
Righteous and worthy of emulation.
You liked him.
Like a son.
Well. he didn't die.
Will he come home?
Soon.
To take revenge.
At full strength.
I'll do the talking.
No one must know who you are.
Maybe we shouldn't have hired a security guard.
If we encounter danger along the way.
we'll thank God that we have it.
Get moving!
I have a message.
Wait!
Eumaeus sent me!
Find that beggar.
Your men will wait outside.
Weapons. too.
Zeus welcomes you. strangers.
Did you come from far away?
Not really.
Did you come here to relax for the night?
We have come to offer a sacrifice to Athena.
And we will generously reward you
for your hospitality.
Of course.
Take that beggar away.
He has a message for me.
Did Eumaeus send you?
Yes. sir.
Okay. what's the link?
It's personal.
These men…
They are priests.
This is your chance to leave. old man.
Go away. stranger.
I've already spared one old man this week.
But he was blind.
But I won't spare this one.
You held your own pretty well for a beggar.
No one is born a beggar.
Let's take this priest's cloak.
Throw it over your armor.
Help me carry his body away.
We have to leave him here.
No.
We have to get out of here.
That's no way to honor the dead.
That's how you stay alive.
He was my teacher.
Perhaps she took on the form of Athena.
His name was Mentor.
And once you're safe. we'll head west
into the unknown to honor him.
These men were sent by the suitors.
Others are coming; we have to leave.
At night?
It's safer than staying here.
And Mentor rests in the heart
of Athens' oldest temple.
For now. let's honor him with a fire.
Fire!
Fire! Fire!
How could a beggar have known Mentor?
I told you.
I wasn't always a beggar.
There is wisdom in your eyes.
Eyes like Athena's.
Don't look for gods in people.
You'll just end up disappointed.
So tell me. who are you?
My name is Sinon.
An old soldier who fought
under your father's command at Troy.
Did you know my father?
I took orders from him for longer
than I'd care to remember.
Wait. is he alive?
He's alive.
So where is he?
It's nearby.
He sent me ahead
to assess the situation.
My mother won't believe it.
No. you can't tell her that.
What. nothing?
Tell her.
Tell her that you've decided
it's time for her to get married again.
He doesn't have to test my mother.
How can he suspect her?
He doesn't suspect her.
But she has every reason
to forget him.
Are there any faithful servants here?
A few.
One has just proven his loyalty.
We need to gather the suitors at the palace.
That will never be a problem.
Do you have any gifts from Menelaus?
Yes. on my boat.
Okay.
Come back as a prince.
Throw a party.
And I'll be there.
What are you going to do at the reception?
To beg.
The best view of a person is from below.
How many suitors are there?
Tens.
If all his men are like you.
then he doesn't really have any.
What. are you alone?
You. too.
Telemachus has returned.
What?
Who says that?
Everyone says that.
Where is Telemachus?
My queen!
Your place is definitely up there.
Is that true?
You've come home.
I'm back.
I was thinking we could
celebrate it tonight.
If we have something to celebrate.
Don't worry.
My valiant suitors will shower us
with gifts in honor of your return.
I'm really glad
that you came back safe and sound.
It's good to see you back on your feet.
It's time to take you to the palace.
What did you find out about your father?
Nothing.
Stories from the war. but no one knows
what became of him after Troy.
I'm sorry. Mom.
In Sparta. everyone is talking
about the impending disaster.
About the Age of Darkness brought about by the Sea
Nations. who have broken the law of Dia.
Those stories are true.
Our civilization is crumbling.
Menelaus fears that we cannot raise
an army while the throne is vacant.
That's why we came up with a plan.
What's the plan?
The only way
to get suitors to leave.
It's time for you to make a choice.
Do you want me to get married again?
If you get married.
the other suitors will leave.
and then I'll have to
face only one of them.
I'm getting closer to adulthood.
I'll tell the elders that I
learned of Odysseus's death in Sparta.
Menelaus will support me.
and they will allow me to take the throne.
So you'll renounce your father. and I'll leave
my home to live with the serpent?
Is that your plan?
Do you have a better one?
Lock the door. light a fire.
and burn those good-for-nothings alive.
Do you think that if I get married.
life will go back to the way it was?
That world has ended.
And in this world
They won't hand over power
to you or to Odysseus.
And if he were to return.
he would have to kill them.
Just like you.
If you kill them.
their families will seek revenge.
And they'll kick me out.
And without me. the throne will be lost.
Because only men can fill that position.
An Empty Throne?
I sat on that empty throne
for a full twenty years!
My experience and my years of service.
None of that is worth the few hairs
that have grown on your chin.
Do you want peace?
Or do you want revenge?
I want an Odyssey!
Sing. Muse. the story of a single face.
One face.
One fleet.
One war.
in Troy…
Sing. Muse. the story of one man.
One man!
One idea!
What a trick!
Eumaeus. come on in.
Argos.
You have to bury him at the top of the cliff.
Where did you meet?
You are Odysseus.
You are my father.
I'm just a beggar.
And you are
the noble. handsome son of Odysseus.
who. when you finally meet him.
He'll be proud of you.
Welcome home. stranger.
Why the Darkness of Victory
envelops those who create myths.
and turns us into poets and blind beggars.
Please accept Dio's hospitality.
Give the stranger something to eat.
No. sir.
All I need is a bowl for my food.
Today we had to welcome
yet another filthy intruder.
What difference will
one more beggar make at this feast?
We have to kill him before he
regains the elders' favor.
How?
Bring on the wine!
Provoke him and make him grab a weapon.
He's no longer that reckless boy
we used to know.
When we get back tonight.
I'll cut out his tongue.
Now get to work. old man.
Please. I haven't eaten all day.
I said. "Get out!"
You have no right to withhold food
that does not belong to you.
There's no room in your bowl.
It'll fit.
You're welcome.
It really does fit.
Here you go.
I'm guessing you want
something from me now.
No. actually. I have something for you.
Do you have something for me?
Do you have anything for me?
And what could a filthy beggar
like you possibly have that I would want?
Actually. it's yours.
I was asked
to return this to you.
That's not mine.
No?
So where did you get that from?
Don't turn your back on me!
Antinous. you can't
treat a beggar like that.
It is Dia's law.
The Law of Dia?
Do you think this is God?
Do you think he's some kind of
god in disguise?
Are you?
Are you God?
An intruder?
No.
I am a veteran of the Trojan War.
A veteran of the Trojan War.
So. what's your name. veteran?
Sinon.
Does that name ring a bell?
No.
I adopted it in honor of the bravest
boy I ever knew.
Otherwise?
Wasn't that your shepherd's son?
I don't remember.
Yes. yes.
you wanted him to take your place.
Where did you find that?
That's where you'll be soon. too.
And where is that?
In Hád.
Enough is enough!
The party is over!
Bastards.
That's not mine!
The queen would like to speak with you.
Wait until they leave. then start a fire.
Welcome. traveler.
My dear lady.
Melanthó. wash the stranger's feet.
That's not necessary.
My husband insisted that we
treat strangers as we would our own family.
Do you know Odysseus. my husband?
Of course.
And how do you know him?
I was in Troy. my lady.
And maybe these songs
seem funny to you.
They make me cry.
Why?
For what has been lost.
Souls?
And years.
Everything.
Did you know about Odysseus in Troy?
Yes.
Was there anything unusual
about his clothing?
Something he used to wear?
He was wearing an unusual brooch.
Unusual?
She was beautiful. but she seemed out of place.
Describe her to me.
I'll bring some more water.
It was a beautiful gold brooch.
In the center. it took the form of Athena.
surrounded by vine leaves.
Did he wear it often?
He never took it off.
How come you came back home.
but he didn't?
I haven't come back yet.
Not yet.
Why?
Coming home isn't always easy.
That goes for Odysseus
just as much as it does for me.
The Odysseus I knew would have found
his way to me. or he would have fought his way there.
What if the Odysseus you knew
had lost his way?
What if one night
in a strange city
He saw something that convinced him
that the home he knew.
Does it no longer exist?
What if. when he emerged from the horse's belly
and opened the gates of Troy.
Did he see the fury of ten years. which
came crashing down on that city in a single night?
Everyone. come on. now!
We left them a gift. a symbol of peace.
and they welcomed it into their home.
We have violated everything
that is sacred among people.
And we turned the fight into a hunt.
No. please.
The burning of the walls of Troy meant
the burning of the entire world.
including his home.
What if he knew exactly
that very night.
walking through the flames of anarchy and pain…
What if he knew. in the days that followed.
amid the boisterous celebrations.
What exactly did he do?
And what did all of you do?
One man's idea.
And the deceit of one man.
which forever broke the law of Dia.
We lived in a world of palaces and commerce.
and our language was unable to capture its beauty.
until we destroyed it.
Are you those Maritime Nations?
Yes. my queen.
Violations of the Dia Act
are spreading like the plague.
The Bronze Age is crumbling. and perhaps he
couldn't bear the sight of the ruins
what happened anywhere.
especially in his own home.
But Odysseus is alive
and it will be there
when you need it most.
My God. I've been living among its ruins
for quite a long time now.
Bring the suitors at dawn.
And take the weapons out of the hall.
In a few hours. one suitor will be happy.
while the others will fly into a rage
and demand revenge.
They'll provoke you.
but there won't be any weapons at hand.
During the exam.
the doors will be locked.
I will marry the one
who passes my test.
How do we deal with suitors?
Not us.
Their blood will be on my hands.
or you'll face exile.
Anyway.
Just make sure
they don't get their hands on any weapons.
I'll take care of that.
Even with just one weapon.
there are too many of them.
And you won't have a gun.
I'll have a gun.
Your mother took care of it.
Call together the servants you trust.
And lock the weapons in the upper compartment.
Yes. yes. yes. yes.
All right. all right. wait a minute.
All right. all right.
It seems like he's only interested in the result.
What will the exam be like?
For many years. while my husband was away.
You took over this palace
and feasted there.
And your excuse was
that you wanted to marry me.
And while I was listening
to your celebrations. your arguments.
your mistreatment of my servants
and your disrespect for my house.
I wanted nothing more than for Odysseus
to return and see it all.
But last night I realized
that he isn't here.
He'll never come back.
That's why I'm ready to marry
any man.
who can draw this bow and shoot
an arrow through twelve axes.
Get out.
Show me who you are.
Eumaeus.
Who will be first?
Give me that bow.
That's impossible.
You!
My lord. Odysseus did it with ease.
Then you do it.
I'll wait until it's my turn.
What if we heated the bow
and oiled it?
This bow hasn't been drawn in years.
It's your turn.
No need.
My queen said what she wanted to say.
We cannot take Odysseus's place.
Some of us have always known that.
And others would have followed that great man
to Troy. if he had allowed us to.
But he never came back.
So choose the best
man among us.
We all failed your test.
Not me.
Someone should take those beggars away.
The door is locked
until the exam is over.
The exam is over.
I want to give it a try.
That's enough. old man.
He has the right to try.
And if you don't do it.
let him try.
You're making fun of your mother's wish.
My mother's wish is
for all of you to burn to ashes.
He's an old archer.
Hurry up!
Watch an expert at work.
Foot-licker!
Come on.
Old Man. forget about it.
Hey. man!
Hurry up!
All right. buddy. that's enough.
Leave him alone. Let's go.
You're Ody…
Your place really is down there.
Is that him?
That's him!
Guard the weapon.
Where are the weapons?
In stock upstairs.
Catch him!
What are you waiting for?
It's going to kill us all!
Mom. go outside!
I told you so.
You're making a scene here. you lout.
No! No!
Eumaeus! Let me out!
Down!
No!
Lock the door!
Bring the shields. bring the shields!
Copies!
Use copies!
You thought you were going to kill us all.
I'll kill you. too.
Finish it.
Dad!
When you get to Hades.
tell my men.
that I will go west
and keep my oath.
And tell Sinon
that I have avenged your shame.
What happened?
Did he beat them?
Did he die?
We have severed the fragile bonds
between people.
And throughout the following
centuries of darkness
...stories about Troy…
…they will speak
only in songs.
Odysseus.
Yes. my love.
My love. you cannot die.
Finally. at the end.
To see my beloved.
if I may. one last time.
No. no. no. no.
you can't. you can't.
Not now. not now. please.
please. it's over.
You can't die.
Not death.
Exile.
Telemachus will be king.
We'll go west together. into the unknown.
so that I may honor my men.
Build the fastest ship.
gather the best
Gather your crew and sail toward the horizon.
We'll chase the setting sun.
Why will those stories only be sung?
Because songs will be the only thing
they'll have
In memory of those
who knew how to write.
One war...
Civilization will be reborn.
One man...
And a new dawn will break over the dark world.
And once again. our mistakes will be forgotten.
Translated into Slovak by: .::Ojvih777::.
www.Opensubtitles.org